 [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements about asexual reproduction is correct?",
      "options": [
        "always involves one parent but the offspring are genetically different from the parent",
        "may involve two parents but the offspring is always identical to one parent.",
        "always involves one parent and the offspring are identical to the parent",
        "involves two parents but the offspring is not genetically identical to any of the parents."
      ],
      "answer": " always involves one parent and the offspring are identical to the parent "
    },
    {
      "question": "A group of closely related organisms capable of interbreeding to produce fertile offspring are known as members of a",
      "options": [
        "kingdom",
        "class",
        "family",
        "specie"
      ],
      "answer": " specie "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following conditions in flowering plants enhances self-pollination?",
      "options": [
        "cleistogamy",
        "heterostyly",
        "protandry",
        "protogyny"
      ],
      "answer": " protandry "
    },
    {
      "question": "The natural dwelling place of an organism is called",
      "options": [
        "ecological niche",
        "habitat",
        "population",
        "environment"
      ],
      "answer": " habitat "
    },
    {
      "question": "Movement of water across a semi-permeable membrane from a weaker solution to a stronger solution is known as",
      "options": [
        "transpiration",
        "diffusion",
        "active transport",
        "osmosis"
      ],
      "answer": "osmosis "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an abiotic factor which affects a population?",
      "options": [
        "Temperature",
        "Producer",
        "Consumer",
        "Parasite"
      ],
      "answer": " Temperature "
    },
    {
      "question": "An inferior ovary of a flower is situated",
      "options": [
        "below the floral parts",
        "above the floral parts",
        "at the same level with the floral parts",
        "at the centre of the floral parts"
      ],
      "answer": " below the floral parts "
    },
    {
      "question": "Conservation may be promoted by",
      "options": [
        "encouraging tree plants",
        "deforestation",
        "overgrazing",
        "bush burning"
      ],
      "answer": " encouraging tree plants "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a biotic components of an ecosystem?",
      "options": [
        "Soil",
        "Rainfall",
        "Light",
        "Fungi"
      ],
      "answer": " Fungi "
    },
    {
      "question": "The process by which plants manufacture their food from carbondioxide and water using energy from the sun is called",
      "options": [
        "chemosynthesis",
        "photosynthesis",
        "anabolism",
        "catabolism"
      ],
      "answer": " photosynthesis "
    },
    {
      "question": "Rhizobium which lives in the root nodules of leguminous plants is an example of association known as",
      "options": [
        "commensalism",
        "epiphytism",
        "mutualism",
        "saprophytism"
      ],
      "answer": " mutualism "
    },
    {
      "question": "Ecology simply means the study of",
      "options": [
        "the properties of a habitat",
        "inter-relationship between organisms and their environment",
        "several species of plants and animals",
        "inter-relationship between plants and animals"
      ],
      "answer": " inter-relationship between organisms and their environment "
    },
    {
      "question": "A population is best described as",
      "options": [
        "a group of organisms of the same species living together",
        "a group of animals and plants living together",
        "a group of insects and grasses",
        "different species of wild animals"
      ],
      "answer": " a group of organisms of the same species living together "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following instruments is not used in measuring abiotic factors in a habitat",
      "options": [
        "wind vane",
        "thermometer",
        "microscope",
        "hygrometer"
      ],
      "answer": " microscope "
    },
    {
      "question": "The term syncarpous is used to described a flower when the carpels are",
      "options": [
        "many and fused",
        "two only",
        "two and nectar",
        "lying at different parts of a flower"
      ],
      "answer": " many and fused "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following structures are characteristics of insect pollinated flowers?",
      "options": [
        "Dull coloured flowers with no nectar",
        "Very light, numerous and peridulous stamen",
        "Brightly coloured petals, scent and nectar",
        "Flowers are usually small and inconspicuous"
      ],
      "answer": " Brightly coloured petals, scent and nectar "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an advantage of dispersal of fruits and seeds? It allows",
      "options": [
        "fair distribution of source of food for animals",
        "growth in close association with parent plant",
        "even distribution of plants and reduction of intra specific competition",
        "the seeds to evolve new species"
      ],
      "answer": " even distribution of plants and reduction of intra specific competition "
    },
    {
      "question": "The series of changes that occur in a seed by which the embryo develops into a seedling is known as",
      "options": [
        "fertilizer",
        "gametogenesis",
        "pollination",
        "germination"
      ],
      "answer": " germination "
    },
    {
      "question": "An association between two organisms in which both benefit is called",
      "options": [
        "parasitism",
        "commensalism",
        "symbiosis",
        "predation"
      ],
      "answer": " symbiosis "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following pairs consists of gametes?",
      "options": [
        "Ova and spermatozoan",
        "Spores and sporangium",
        "Flowers and pollen grains",
        "Testes and ovaries"
      ],
      "answer": " Ova and spermatozoan "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these groups of organisms is responsible for capturing energy for the biotic community?",
      "options": [
        "Decomposers",
        "Omnivore",
        "Consumers",
        "Producers"
      ],
      "answer": " Producers "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these is not true characteristics of the tropical rain forest?",
      "options": [
        "Vegetation consists predominantly of tall trees with thick canopy",
        "Forest is rich in epiphytes and climbers",
        "Annual rainfall is less than 100cm",
        "Fruits of trees are often large sized and are generally without adaptation to wind dispersal"
      ],
      "answer": " Annual rainfall is less than 100cm "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a way of conserving natural resources?",
      "options": [
        "Adopting good farming practices",
        "Establishing forest reserves",
        "Establishing game reserves",
        "Encouraging poaching"
      ],
      "answer": " Encouraging poaching "
    },
    {
      "question": "The transfer of pollen grains from the anther to the stigma of the same flower is known as",
      "options": [
        "fertilization",
        "self pollination",
        "reproduction",
        "conjugation"
      ],
      "answer": " self pollination "
    },
    {
      "question": "Respiration is an essential life process providing the living cells with",
      "options": [
        "carbondioxide",
        "energy",
        "sugars",
        "glycogen"
      ],
      "answer": " energy "
    },
    {
      "question": "A major pollutant around airport residential areas is",
      "options": [
        "oil spillage",
        "soot",
        "noise",
        "dust"
      ],
      "answer": " noise "
    },
    {
      "question": "The feeding relationship between the organisms labelled III and IV is",
      "options": [
        "parasitism",
        "mutualism",
        "predation",
        "saprophytism"
      ],
      "answer": " predation "
    },
    {
      "question": "The producer is",
      "options": [
        "I because it contains the least amount of energy",
        "I because it uses sunlight to manufacture food",
        "IV because it is the largest organism in the diagram",
        "IV because it is the organism that receives the highest amount of sunlight."
      ],
      "answer": " I because it uses sunlight to manufacture food "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not part of the male reproductive system?",
      "options": [
        "Penis",
        "Testes",
        "Uterus",
        "Prostate gland"
      ],
      "answer": " Uterus "
    },
    {
      "question": "About how long does the menstrual cycle takes?",
      "options": [
        "5days",
        "25days",
        "14days",
        "28days"
      ],
      "answer": "28days "
    },
    {
      "question": "What is a zygote?",
      "options": [
        "A cell formed when two embryos join which will develop into a gamete",
        "A cell formed when two gametes join which will develop into a gland",
        "A cell formed when two gametes join which will develop into an embryo",
        "A cell formed when two gland meet to produce an hormone"
      ],
      "answer": " A cell formed when two gametes join which will develop into an embryo "
    },
    {
      "question": "Ovulation is best defined as",
      "options": [
        "the release of mature egg cell",
        "the loss of the endometrium lining of the uterus",
        "the joining of a sperm and an egg",
        "the cell passing through the fallopian tube"
      ],
      "answer": " the release of mature egg cell "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which hormone is responsible for the development of male secondary sexual characteristics?",
      "options": [
        "Luitenizing hormone",
        "oestrogen",
        "progesterone",
        "testosterone"
      ],
      "answer": " testosterone "
    },
    {
      "question": "In reproduction, what is fertilization?",
      "options": [
        "When a male and female gamete join",
        "When a farmer puts manure on farmland",
        "When a plant drop seeds onto the ground",
        "The ripening of egg cell"
      ],
      "answer": " When a male and female gamete join "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement about flowering plants is correct?",
      "options": [
        "The stamen is the female part of the flower and comprises the filament and anther",
        "The stamen is the male part of the flower and comprises the filament and anther",
        "The carpel is the female part of the flower and comprises the ovary and filament",
        "The stamen consists of pistil and anther"
      ],
      "answer": " The stamen is the male part of the flower and comprises the filament and anther "
    },
    {
      "question": "How are the pollen grains of insect pollinated plants adapted for transfer?",
      "options": [
        "They are smooth and light",
        "They are produced in very large amounts",
        "They are sticky and brightly coloured",
        "Flowers have no scent, no nectar"
      ],
      "answer": " They are sticky and brightly coloured "
    },
    {
      "question": "The transfer of pollen grain from the anther to the stigma of a flower to another of the same species is known as",
      "options": [
        "self pollination",
        "cross pollination",
        "germination",
        "fertilization"
      ],
      "answer": " cross pollination "
    },
    {
      "question": "The arrangement of the ovules in the ovary is known as",
      "options": [
        "syncarpous",
        "pollination",
        "marginal",
        "placentation"
      ],
      "answer": " placentation "
    },
    {
      "question": "When a flower contains both pistil and stamen it is referred to as",
      "options": [
        "complete flower",
        "incomplete flower",
        "hermaphrodite flower",
        "imperfect flower"
      ],
      "answer": " complete flower "
    },
    {
      "question": "The type of reproduction in which eggs are released from the female parents body to hatch and develop in external environment is termed",
      "options": [
        "viviparity",
        "oviparity",
        "ovoviviparity",
        "desiccation"
      ],
      "answer": " oviparity "
    },
    {
      "question": "An effective management of natural resources to ensure their continuous yield from generation to generation may involve all the following except",
      "options": [
        "protection of wildlife",
        "prevention of habitat destruction",
        "biological control of pests",
        "disposal of raw sewage into the sea"
      ],
      "answer": " disposal of raw sewage into the sea "
    },
    {
      "question": "the type of asexual reproduction in which part of an organism breaks up to give rise to a new individual is known as",
      "options": [
        "spore formation",
        "budding",
        "fragmentation",
        "vegetative propagation"
      ],
      "answer": " fragmentation "
    },
    {
      "question": "The drugs which inhibit the growth of disease-causing organisms and thus used in the treatment of infections are referred to as",
      "options": [
        "antibodies",
        "antibiotics",
        "anti-toxics",
        "septics"
      ],
      "answer": " antibiotics "
    },
    {
      "question": "Organisms that feed essentially on plants within an ecosystem may be referred to as",
      "options": [
        "carnivores",
        "herbivores",
        "saprophytes",
        "omnivores"
      ],
      "answer": " herbivores "
    },
    {
      "question": "Endangered species are organisms that ought to be",
      "options": [
        "hunted",
        "killed",
        "poached",
        "protected"
      ],
      "answer": " protected "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following substances is not a conservable natural resources?",
      "options": [
        "Mineral",
        "Soil",
        "Water",
        "Air"
      ],
      "answer": " Air "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following male reproductive organs help in the production of sperm?",
      "options": [
        "Vas deferens",
        "Epididymis",
        "Prepuce",
        "Seminiferous tubules"
      ],
      "answer": " Seminiferous tubules "
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following female reproductive system represents a penis and erectile in nature?",
      "options": [
        "Cervix",
        "Fallopian tube",
        "Clitoris",
        "Uterus"
      ],
      "answer": " Clitoris "
    },
    {
      "question": "Sperm is stored in the",
      "options": [
        "prostrate gland",
        "seminiferous tubule",
        "testes",
        "epididymis"
      ],
      "answer": " epididymis "
    },
    {
      "question": "The male sexual reproductive organ in flowering plant is",
      "options": [
        "corolla",
        "sepal",
        "gynoecium",
        "androecium"
      ],
      "answer": " androecium "
    }
  ]
